## Contact

felipelino44@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/felipelino (LinkedIn) github.com/felipelino (Portfolio)

## Top Skills

**API REST** 

AWS Elastic Beanstalk

AWS Lambda

## Languages

Inglês (Full Professional)

Português (Native or Bilingual)

## Certifications

Docker Crash Course for busy DevOps and Developers

M103: Basic Cluster Administration

Understanding and Developing

Emotional Intelligence

M220J: MongoDB for Java

Developers

Negotiation Secrets for Master Negotiators

### Honors-Awards

**Honorable Mention** 

Honorable Mention

### **Publications**

Work In Progress - Analyzer and Simulator of Petri Nets

## Felipe Lino

Developer at Critical TechWorks

Barreiro, Setúbal, Portugal

## Summary

Recently I have been working as a Principal Engineer at Farfetch. Dealing with technologies like: Kubernetes, Helm Charts, REST APIs, Kafka. Helping teams, define process and collaborate to grow the company.

I also had experience as Tech Team Lead at B2W, where I could work in several projects for the Marketplace.

I participated in the evolution of the technological monolithic systems for the most modern ones that make use of decoupled APIs from a front-end.

Personal Github: https://github.com/felipelino/

## Experience

Critical TechWorks
Senior Software Engineer
April 2024 - Present (1 year 7 months)

Lisboa, Lisboa, Portugal

Work in the Team responsible to develop an Internal Portal to be used by BMW Group related to Confluent Kafka where users are able to create and configure Kafka Topics, Confluent Connectors, see status, check costs among other features.

The mains technology used is: Kotlin and related frameworks, Angular 2, Database Postgres,

Kafka, Kubernetes, CI/CD Github Actions

Following the methodology SCRUM.

My main contribution was to improve the Refinement Process of the team, the Deployment process now more reliable and faster. From a technical perspective was to enable the use of an internal type of connector created by BMW within the Portal.

#### **FARFETCH**

5 years 8 months

Principal Engineer April 2023 - February 2024 (11 months)

Lisboa, Portugal

Follow my role as Principal Engineer (Interim) now as effective.

Acting at least in this 3 dimensions:

- 1.Technical support help: where I'm more "hands-on" in code helping the team that requires more help at that moment for a given subject.
- 2. Support team leaders in the technical side: the Team Lead may need technical help to take decisions once they are more close to Management than the technical. As Principal interim it is my responsibility advice and help them
- 3. Pursue subjects common to the cluster: There are some subjects that affect several teams. It is my responsibility as Principal to follow them and contribute, so the result of a discussion can bring benefits for all.

With this in mind recently I achieve results as:

- Help teams to migrate micro-services to adopt Azure Kubernetes Service, with Helm, ArgoCD and Jenkins as CI tool.
- Support them with Java, once most of the teams don't have experts Java developers.
- Help to define Open API Specs and Avro contracts
- Help to build API Gateway with Kong

Principal Engineer (Interim)

January 2022 - April 2023 (1 year 4 months)

Lisboa, Portugal

One of the greatest achievements in this period was migrate a .NET 2.1 Public API to Azure Kubernetes Service + Kong (as API Gateway). Saving costs and reducing development cycle. I had to plan, deal with several development teams that share the ownership of the service and infrastructure.

Senior Software Engineer .NET/Java July 2018 - August 2022 (4 years 2 months) Lisboa e Região, Portugal

I worked in the "Acquisition team" between 2018/Jul - 2019/Nov . This team is responsible to share information about the catalog of products with third

parties as Products Up, Criteo, Facebook, Google Shopping among others. I helped the team to re-design a flow from batch to near-real-time approach to update the information in our partners as soon as possible. We used technologies as .Net, Java, Cassandra, Docker Containers and Kafka.

After 2019/Nov I joined another team responsible to improve the SEO in Farfetch Website. I helped to re-design some services decoupling management APIs (Used by internal management tools) and runtimes APIs (used by Farfetch website). Migrating data to MongoDB (for managemen) and prepare data for queries with Cassandra (runtime)

B2W Digital
Senior Software Engineer Team Lead
July 2014 - June 2018 (4 years)
Rio de Janeiro e Região, Brasil

B2W Digital is the biggest e-commerce in Brazil owner of this brands:

Americanas.com, Submarino and Shoptime. Here, I was the technical leader of the team responsible for APIs and Web tools for management of the Buy box as well as generation of metrics and interpretation of results. Through our APIs we have been able to increase the conversion rate on purchases made on the site and also customize the result by showing the best purchase offer for our customers.

In the same company I acted as a Technical Lead working on Corporate Services Team. We work with microservices, REST, defining process and tools. These tools are used for other developers in the company. We build a Web App responsible to manage the micro-services that runs in our custom Platform As A Service (PAAS)

Technologies: RAML, REST, Java, Angular JS (1 & 2), Docker, Amazon AWS, Cassandra, Mongo DB, and others.

Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro Substitute College Professor October 2008 - February 2015 (6 years 5 months) Rio de Janeiro Area. Brazil

UERJ is one of the best universities in Brazil, there I was working as a professor, teaching classes for undergraduate students in Computer Science and Information Technology. The subjects taught are:

- Algorithms and Data Structures: which are introduced in the issues of algorithms, trees, vector manipulation, recursion, linked lists, hash tables, lists, priority;

- Operational Systems I: , the subjects covered are: competition process , CPU scheduling, memory management, management of input / output, basic features of an OS, OS main modules, processes, threads, architecture modeling with Petri nets among others;
- Computer Programming I: covering the basics of Language C;
- Distributed Systems: Architecture, distributed process, communication (RMI, RPC, CORBA, Socket, Queues), Integration (EAI / SOA), synchronization, consistence and replication;
- Data Process Introduction: convering the basics of language Pascal;
- Introduction to Informatics: was a course for Economic Science classes on UERJ covering about technology in general.

Other activities consisted of: preparing for exams, exercises and maintenance of page of the disciplines (https://sites.google.com/site/linouerj).

#### Ideais

Senior Software Engineer August 2013 - July 2014 (1 year)

Rio de Janeiro Area, Brazil

We create the REST APIs used by sellers on Marketplace for the ecommerces of B2W.

With this, the partners who integrated with our systems manually by exchanging emails with spreadsheets, could do it automatically, with more security and agility. So the company was able to launch a campaign to attract even more stores to be part of the marketplace.

Technologies: Java 7, tomcat 7 server, Swagger (for contract definition).

PS: The company was bought by B2W Digital in 2014.

#### Indra

Senior Software Engineer December 2010 - July 2013 (2 years 8 months)

Rio de Janeiro Area, Brazil

We develop a set of web applications where employees in the technical areas of the company had greater ease in carrying out their research and information exchange between sectors.

These tools were developed in Java and Python over the enterprise search tool Microsoft Fast ESP in project for Petrobras (biggest Petroleum Company in Latin America), to search documents in: Lotus Notes, Network Drive and Oracle Database.

Ideais

Senior Software Engineer and Team Lead April 2008 - November 2010 (2 years 8 months)

Rio de Janeiro Area, Brazil

As Team Leader from January 2010 - November 2010. I've lead the team who developed the systems related to the backend's sales catalog of Americanas.com and Shoptime.

We achieve the purpose of facilitating the configuration of the products of the brands composing B2W, since the systems that are unique handle. This gave to the marketing area more agility and increase the sales.

We create applications to synchronize the updates made by the user area (price, promotions, formation of kits, update sheet) on products to the website. Technologies: Spring, Solr (for search), Hibernate, Spring-WS. And we use agile development methodology based on Scrum, using approaches such as TDD (Test Driven Domain).

Software Engineer (senior) from April 2008 - January 2010. I act in the development of Customer Service Management System for B2W, to integrate the customer service of the 3 brands (Americanas.com, Submarino.com and Shoptime) in a single tool.

The solution adopted was assuming the use of tools from Oracle / BEA Workspace Studio and WebLogic Server 10.

We used technologies like Spring, Spring WS for communication with Web Services, Hibernate with JPA, Page Flow as MVC (Page Flow is an extension of Struts developed by BEA)

Besides developer team I worked as Mini-leader, responsible for packet generation, customer relationship, defining development strategies and assist the lead in the division of tasks among the other team members.

Accenture Services 2 years 3 months

Full System Analyst May 2007 - April 2008 (1 year)

Rio de Janeiro Area, Brazil

Implementation of Bus SOA (Service Bus) in telecom company Oi / Telemar. The solution adopted by Oi uses tools from BEA: AquaLogic Service Bus, WebLogic Integration and AquaLogic Data Services running on the application server WebLogic Server 8.1 and WebLogic Server 9.2.

The project consisted of implementing the first corporate services to be provided in Service Bus, defining policies, standards and procedures to be

followed for the development of new services. Establishing a communication pattern between the high and low platforms of enterprise legacy systems.

#### Trainee

February 2006 - May 2007 (1 year 4 months)

Worked in Factory of Enterprise Application Integration (EAI) Accenture in Oi Project at all stages of development from requirements: Technical Specification (TS), Peer review, Construction and Unit Testing, Code Review and Deploy. Elaborating further supporting documentation for Implementation: Migration Script, Run Book and Release Notes.

Assist the team to ensure adherence to the Methodology Accenture.

Developing in Java, PL-SQL and Shell Scripts, working on Solaris Unix environment.

Enterprise Application Integration it is a concept of integration between distributed applications in Brazil, it was used mainly for major telecommunications companies such as GVT, BrasilTelecom (BrT), Embratel, Telemar Group (Oi), etc.

The tool used in EAI integration solution of Oi (Telemar Group) is the Vitria BusinessWare based on technologies: Java, CORBA and XML.

Major demands developed:

- Integration Solution for Simple Orders between the CRM system of fixed telephony (STC, Mainframe), the mobile CRM system (Siebel), the activation platform (Initiator) and the prepaid system. The adopted solution makes use of various technologies such as CORBA, XML and JDBC.
- Auto Deploy Solution. The solution was divided into 2 parts, the first is that the generation of the package and the second being deploy itself. To achieve this Shell-scripts were developed and was made using Ant to do versioning repository access of sources (PVCS), compilation of files, packet generation and later deploy.

# Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro Instructor

March 2005 - December 2005 (10 months)

Rio de Janeiro Area, Brazil

Instructor of discipline Computer Programming II (Java) at UERJ. The activities performed were:

- a. Answer questions from students of the discipline
- b. Preparation of lists of exercise
- c. Correction of lists of exercise
- d. Working in VAS Project Verification of Software Architecture

To carry out the activities it was necessary to have a domain of Java and object-oriented programming.

The VAS Project is a research project that deals with the verification of software architecture by using formal methods and mathematical architecture description languages (ADLs), in particular the language CBabel. During the project was produced a case study showing the potential of CBabel ADL and its usefulness as a plug-in and was done for the Eclipse IDE for editing in Cbabel.

## Education

Universidade do Estado do Rio de Janeiro
Bachelor's Degree in Informatics and Information Technology, Information
Technology · (2003 - 2007)